mayoclinic.org 2019-12-31

# Privacy policy - About This Site - Mayo Clinic

This policy was last updated on August 13, 2019.

### Web privacy policy

We take your privacy seriously, and we want you to know how we collect, use, share and protect your information. In addition to this privacy policy, users of the Mayo Clinic site should consult the Mayo Clinic site terms of use as well as any product specific terms and conditions that apply. You may review [policies](https://www.mayo.edu/pmts/mc5200-mc5299/mc5256-01.pdf) specifically related to patient information (protected health information, or PHI) submitted through Mayo Clinic's patient portal. This policy applies to MayoClinic.org, MayoClinic.edu and other Web locations under Mayo Clinic's control. Other Mayo Clinic online properties may have their own privacy policies that apply to those sites. You should review those privacy policies in connection with your use of those sites.

### What information we collect

 **Information you give us:** We respect the right to privacy of all visitors to the Mayo Clinic sites. We receive and store information you enter on our sites or give us in any other way, such as name, email address and phone number. This includes information you submit on forms, such as appointment request forms. Some forms collect sensitive information, such as health information, necessary for us to provide our services to you.

**Information we collect automatically:** When you interact with our sites, certain information about your use of our sites is automatically collected. This information includes computer and connection information, such as statistics on your page views, traffic to and from our sites, referral URL, ad data, your IP address, and device identifiers. This information also may include your transaction history, and your web log information, how you search for our sites, the websites you click on from our sites or emails, whether and when you open our emails, and your browsing activities across other websites.

Much of this information is collected through cookies, web beacons and other tracking technologies, as well as through your web browser or device (e.g., IP address, MAC address, browser version, etc.).

### Email communications, newsletter and related services

MayoClinic.org provides you with the opportunity to receive communications from us or third parties. You can sign up for a free Mayo Clinic House Call email newsletter. You can unsubscribe from this newsletter at any time.

Email communications that you send to us via the email links on our site may be shared with a customer service representative, employee, medical expert or agent that is most able to address your inquiry. We make every effort to respond in a timely fashion once communications are received. Once we have responded to your communication, it is discarded or archived, depending on the nature of the inquiry.

The email functionality on our site does not provide a completely secure and confidential means of communication. It's possible that your email communication may be accessed or viewed by another internet user while in transit to us. If you wish to keep your communication private, do not use our email.

You may decide at some point that you no longer wish to receive communications from our site. To stop receiving communications, send an email message to [mayoinfo@mayoclinic.com](mailto:mayoinfo@mayoclinic.com) or send regular mail to the following postal address:

  1. Mayo Privacy Officer
  2. MayoClinic.org
  3. 200 First St. SW
  4. Rochester, MN 55905

### Surveys

We occasionally survey visitors to our site. The information from these surveys is used in aggregated, de-identified form to help us understand the needs of our visitors so that we can improve our site. The information may be shared with third parties with whom we have a business relationship. We generally do not ask for information in surveys that would personally identify you; if we do request contact information for follow-up, you may decline to provide it. If survey respondents provide personal information (such as an email address) in a survey, it is shared only with those people who need to see it to respond to the question or request, or with third parties who perform data management services for our site. Those third parties have agreed to keep all data from surveys confidential.

### How we use the information we collect

We use the information we collect for things like:

  * Optimizing the performance and user experience of our sites
  * Operating, evaluating and improving our business
  * Fulfilling orders and requests for products, services or information
  * Processing returns and exchanges
  * Tracking and confirming online orders
  * Delivering or installing products
  * Marketing and advertising products and services, including identifying you on our websites and tailoring advertisements and offers to you (both on our websites and on other websites) based on your interactions with us in our stores and online
  * Conducting research and analysis
  * Communicating with you about your account, special events and surveys
  * Establishing and managing your accounts with us

We may combine this information with any other information we have about you, including, if you are a Mayo Clinic Patient, any PHI we have about you. If we combine this information with your PHI, we will treat all of that information as PHI, and will only use or disclose that information as set forth in our notice of privacy practices.

### Data retention

We will retain your information for as long as your account is active or as needed to provide you services, comply with our legal obligations, resolve disputes and enforce our agreements.

### We may share information with third parties

We may share the information we collect about you with third parties who we have engaged to help us provide the services. In each case, we will ensure that these third parties have agreed to safeguard your data.

We may provide third parties with aggregate statistics about our visitors, traffic patterns and related site information. These data reflect site-usage patterns gathered during visits to our website each month, but they do not contain information that personally identifies you unless you have given us permission to share that information.

We may use or disclose your personal information if required to do so by law or on the good-faith belief that such action is necessary to (a) conform to applicable law or comply with legal process served on us or our sites; (b) protect and defend our rights or property, the sites or our users, or (c) act to protect the personal safety of us, users of the sites or the public.

### Interest-based advertising and your choices

Use of Cookies: Our sponsors and advertisers and their ad servers may use cookies when you view pages on our site. They use those cookies to collect information as a way of measuring the effectiveness of their advertising, or to provide advertisements about goods and services that may be of interest to you or to avoid running the same ads to you over time. Such information may include your browser type, your operating system, web pages visited, time of visits, content viewed, ads viewed and other clickstream data. We do not control these third parties' use of cookies or how they manage the information they gather through them. However, our sponsors and advertisers have agreed that they will not collect any personally identifiable information from our site visitors while they are on MayoClinic.org. If you click on an advertisement on MayoClinic.org and visit a site maintained by one of our sponsors or advertisers, please be aware that we are not responsible for the privacy practices of that site. You should read the privacy policies of each site you visit to determine what information that site may be collecting about you.

Our partner, Everyday Health, may use a third party ad network provider, Collective Media, to help present advertisements on this website.

Your browser or device may include "Do Not Track" functionality. At this time, we do not respond to browser "Do Not Track" signals.

**Opting out:** You can learn more about the companies we work with that collect information on our websites and who serve advertisements to you on our websites using the links below. The resources below also contain opt-out links.

  * Opt-out for advertisers who work specifically with us: <http://info.evidon.com/more_info/1936>
  * Our advertisers who participate in the Facebook/Nielsen program: 
    * <https://www.facebook.com/help/?faq=211774365532736#What-is-the-Nielsen-partnership-with-Facebook-and-how-does-it-affect-me>
    * <http://www.nielsen-online.com/privacy.jsp?section=leg_scs>
  * Participants in the Network Advertising Initiative ([http://optout.networkadvertising.org](http://optout.networkadvertising.org/)) and the Digital Advertising Alliance ([http://optout.aboutads.info](http://optout.aboutads.info/)). 
  * Opting out of mobile advertising: 
    * Apple: <http://support.apple.com/kb/HT4228>
    * Android: <http://www.google.com/policies/technologies/ads/>
  * We use Google Analytics, a web analytics service provided by Google Inc., on our sites. Google Analytics uses cookies or other tracking technologies to help us analyze how users interact with and use the sites, compile reports on the sites' activity, and provide other services related to sites activity and usage. The technologies used by Google may collect information such as your IP address, time of visit, whether you are a return visitor and any referring website. The sites do not use Google Analytics to gather information that personally identifies you. The information generated by Google Analytics will be transmitted to and stored by Google and will be subject to Google's privacy policy: <https://policies.google.com/?hl=en>. To learn more about Google's partner services and to learn how to opt out of tracking of analytics by Google click here: <https://policies.google.com/technologies/partner-sites>

Please note that opting-out of advertising networks services does not mean that you will not receive advertising while using our sites or on other websites, nor will it prevent the receipt of interest-based advertising from third parties that do not participate in these programs. It will, however, exclude you from interest-based advertising conducted through participating networks, as provided by their policies and choice mechanisms. If you delete your cookies, you may also delete your opt-out preferences.

**Your choices:** By contacting us using the information below, you may:

  * Stop receiving marketing or promotional emails, direct mail, phone and mobile marketing communications from Mayo Clinic
  * Update and correct your personal information
  * Cancel your account or request that we no longer use your information to provide you services

### Security

Whether you are visiting the Mayo Clinic site or in one of our clinic locations, we use reasonable security measures to protect the confidentiality of personal information under our control and appropriately limit access to it. We use a variety of information security measures to protect your online transactions with us. The Mayo Clinic site uses encryption technology, such as Secure Sockets Layer (SSL), to protect your personal information during data transport. SSL protects information you submit via our website, such as ordering information including your name, address and credit card number. That being said, Mayo Clinic cannot ensure or warrant the security of any information you transmit to us, and you do so at your own risk. We have taken reasonable steps to ensure the integrity and confidentiality of personally identifiable information that you may provide. You should understand, however, that electronic transmissions via the internet are not necessarily secure from interception, and so we cannot absolutely guarantee the security or confidentiality of such transmissions.

### Users in the European Economic Area (EEA) and Switzerland

If you are a resident of the EEA or Switzerland, the following information applies with respect to personal data collected through your use of our site.

**Purposes of processing and legal basis for processing:** As explained above, we process personal data in various ways depending upon your use of the services. We process personal data on the following legal bases: (1) with your consent; (2) as necessary to provide the services; and (3) as necessary for our legitimate interests in providing the services where those interests do not override your fundamental rights and freedom related to data privacy.

**Transfers:** Personal data we collect may be transferred to, and stored and processed in, the United States or any other country in which we or our affiliates or processors maintain facilities. We will ensure that transfers of personal data to a country or an international organization outside the EEA or Switzerland are subject to appropriate safeguards.

**Your rights:** You are entitled to the rights under Chapter III of the EU General Data Protection Regulation or Section 2 of the Swiss Federal Act on Data Protection with respect to the processing of your personal data, which include the right to access and rectify and to request erasure of personal data. In order to verify your identity, we may require you to provide us with personal information prior to accessing any records containing information about you.

### Protecting children's privacy

We are committed to protecting children's privacy on the internet, and we do not knowingly collect personal information from children.

### Links to other websites

Our websites link to other websites, many of which have their own privacy policies. Be sure to review the privacy policy on the site you're visiting.

### Privacy policy updates

We may need to update our privacy policy as technology changes and Mayo Clinic evolves. If we make significant changes to the privacy policy, we'll post a prominent message on our websites.

### Your California privacy rights

We do not share your personal information with unaffiliated third parties for their direct marketing purposes. We may, however, share your personal data with any Mayo entity or affiliate. You have the right to contact us and opt-out of such sharing for marketing purposes.

### Contact information

If you have a question or concern regarding your privacy, please contact Mayo Clinic's Privacy Officer using the contact information below:

  1. Mayo Clinic Privacy Officer
  2. 200 First St. SW
  3. Rochester, MN 55905
  4. 507-266-6286
  5. dlenterpriseprivacyoffice@mayo.edu

Aug. 23, 2019

. 
  *[PHI]: protected health information
  *[SSL]: Secure Sockets Layer
  *[EEA]: European Economic Area
